Okay, so let's talk about the different
types of power then, different forms of
power, also known as different types of
authority.
Now, there's various
forms of power that one
seems to exert, the one
can exert on someone else.
So these are all the different forms of
power, I'm going to
talk about each of these.
These are not mutually exclusive,
right?
You can have more than one type of power.
So let's go through each of these.
First one here, positional,
positional power, also known as
formal or legitimate power, also
known as authoritative power.
The two common terms really are formal and
legitimate.
Those are the ones that you always see.
Those are the most common terms.
But basically they're based on your
position.
So this is basically saying that you have
a certain authority level, a certain power
simply because of your position,
your position, your job title,
your job description.
That is what gives you that authority.
And that's the only thing that gives you,
authority, right?
So you are a senior director in an
organization, right?
You're a senior director, you have a
certain authority level simply because you
have been promoted to that position,
right?
You're a captain in the army, right?
You have a certain
authority level simply because
of your position, simply
because of your rank.
That's it, and that is all that is giving
you that particular power.
So, you're a project manager.
You have a certain authority level because
you are a project manager.
Now remember, project manager's authority
is documented in the project charter.
So the project charter lists you as a
project manager and your authority level.
That is known as a
formal or legitimate power
or authoritative power
or positional power.
It basically has been assigned to you and
that's the key.
It's been assigned to you.
Now, another type of power then is
something called expert power.
and expert power is
basically saying that you
are recognized as the
subject matter expert.
So if you are in a situation where you
have to make a decision, no one's going to
question your authority because you are
recognized as a subject matter expert.
As a very simple example, let's say you
are in a meeting and in this meeting we're
discussing the direction
of the work and you
say, I think we should take this approach.
well no one's going to question your
authority because you are recognized as
the subject matter expert if anybody knows
you know no one's going to question you
you think we should take this approach
everyone's going to agree all right let's
go take this approach because you are
recognized you are recognized as the
expert in the field so if this could be
based on your knowledge and experience
their subject matter expertise knowledge
and experience based on the skill sets
that you've received rather skill sets
that you have achieved.
It can also be based on
education, some kind of education
that you have or some
certification that you've achieved.
That would all be based on, or rather,
that would all be an expert power.
Now, the key with the expert
power is people recognize
you as the expert power and
therefore it is always earned.
You have to earn your respect,
right?
It's never assigned.
It's always earned.
You have to earn your respect.
Then you've got another
one called reward power and
a couple of ways of looking
at reward power, right?
You may have the authority to offer
financial incentives and perks,
right, to your team members and you use
that to your advantage.
You are the kind of manager that
encourages your staff to perform.
You're the kind of manager that basically
says, you know, if you get this done,
there's a gift card there.
Or if you get this work done and you do a
good job, there's a good job.
a promotion, right, or there's a bonus.
You're encouraging them.
So, you know, I know
you've been working really
hard, right, you've been
putting in long hours.
Let's just get over this last hurdle and
I'll give you some time off in lieu.
So you're recognizing their efforts.
Now, even if you don't have the authority
to offer financial incentives and perks,
you are still the kind of manager that,
again, encourages your team.
You praise them, right?
You're constantly encouraging them.
You're recognizing their efforts.
You let your peers know, your superiors
know, that, hey, this
person did a great job.
You're letting them feel good about the
work that they're doing.
That would be a reward power.
You're letting them know that,
you know, you recognize their efforts.
As opposed to the penalty power,
where you are not recognizing their
efforts, You are not
encouraging your team, you are
constantly threatening
your team to do the work.
You're the kind of
manager that keeps saying,
you better get this done
otherwise, you're fired.
That would be a type of penalty power.
So you're not recognising their efforts.
You're constantly demeaning them, and
they're in constant fear of repercussion.
Your team member, they're in constant fear
of repercussion.
And that is what you believe is really
driving them to do well.
so that would be a penalty power then you
got something called referent power now
referent power is actually quite a wide
term there's quite a few items that fall
under reference power but referent power
is basically people follow you because
they have a great respect for you right
because they have a respect for you that's
why they follow you respect due to for
example your personality or charisma so
because of your personality and your
charisma because of that and nothing else
because of your personality people will
follow you.
you.
You may have absolutely no idea what
you're talking about or what you're doing,
but people just follow you anyway,
right, because of your personality.
That would be a type of referent power.
Another type of referent
power could be something
that you've achieved in the past, right?
Very good example that is given here,
a retired athlete.
10 years ago, 20 years
ago, 30 years ago, right, this
retired athlete may have
been an expert in the field.
they're not an expert in the field now.
I mean, obviously, they can't play
professionally now, but
you have a great respect.
You have a great respect for what they
achieved in the past.
That would be a type of referent power.
Reference power can also be who someone
associates with.
That could be a type of referent power.
So you have a new team member joining your
team.
There are nobody in your organization.
But then you see that they're hanging out
with the CEO and the CFO of your
organization, hanging out with all these
people that high up in your organization,
then you might have a different respect
for them after that.
This person knows something I don't.
So, referent power is, like I said,
is quite a wide term.
There's a few items that fall under
referent power.
Rather, there's a couple of
other items on the following
page that really would be a
type of reference power as well.
Now, that's type of power then is
something called representative power.
I was basically saying that your team
members have decided, you know,
they've basically appointed you to
represent them, right, to make a decision
or, you know, on a particular task, right,
or to lead a meeting or whatever it is.
Right.
So, they have basically voted you in to
represent them.
So that's a representative power.
Then you got these other types of power as
well.
And these first two are a
type of, you know, they're
a type of referent power,
if you like, informational.
So you are recognized as the go-to person
to get certain information, right?
You have the ability to get information of
any kind.
You're that go-to person or something like
situational as well.
So you're a nobody in the organization.
But then a crisis occurs and now you rise
up to the occasion.
And now people have a different respect
for you.
So this is a situation is, you know,
a situation.
occurs, wherever the situation is.
It doesn't have to be
a crisis or anything like
that, but it could just
be any kind of situation.
And, you know, you
perform in a certain way,
and now people have a
different respect for you.
And then we've got these other ones as
well.
These are some of the
minor ones like flattery,
pressure-based,
guilt-based, persuasiveness.
So these are other different forms of
power as well.
So again, remember, you've got all these
different forms of power, right?
They're not mutually exclusive,
right?
You can have more than one of these forms
of power.